Joshua E. Lambert, PhD

Joshuae.Lambert@gmail.com | Website (jelambert.com) | Twitter

Research Interests

I am a Postdoctoral Scholar skilled in computational social science methods. I have experience with econometric methods, natural language processing, machine learning, and geospatial analysis. I have published popular and scholarly work that has looked at various conflict dynamics, political instability, and leader psychology utilizing both qualitative and quantitative methods.

Work Experience

National Center for Integrated Coastal Research

University of Central Florida 2020 – Current

Postdoctoral Scholar - ML/NLP Data Scientist

- Designed a conceptual framework for distilling cross-sectional and longitudinal variation at various governmental jurisdiction aggregations along the United States Gulf Coast.
- Implemented pipeline of Latent Dirichlet Allocation NLP and out-of-sample two-step ensemble classification of determinants for coastal adaptation strategies to climatic conditions.

Kurdish Political Studies Program

University of Central Florida

Graduate Research Associate

2020

 Implemented classification and regression analysis on panel data regarding historical effects of religious characteristics on global instances of civilian victimization, terrorism, and episodes of genocide. Selected to present research at the American Political Science Association conference.

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Adjunct Lecturer

2019-2020

Graduate Teaching Assistant

2016-2018

- Utilized spatial and climatic conditions to better model and forecast the historical instance of coups.
 Dissertation: Food, Familiarity, and Forecasting: Modeling Coups with Computational Methods.
 Selected to present research at the International Studies Association conference.
- Taught the upper-level collegiate course GIS for Political Analysis, Jupyter notebook.

Intelligence Community's Center for Academic Excellence

University of Central Florida

Graduate Research Associate

2018 - 2019

Visiting Research Associate

2016 - 2018

 Managed team of five researchers on the design and development of a longitudinal, cross-national leader speech materials database. Designed and developed website for the open access of data at: Psychological Characteristics of Leaders (PsyCL). Selected to present research at International Society for Political Psychology conference.

Secure Fisheries
One Earth Future
Researcher
2018

 Collaborated with team of interdisciplinary scientists on design and implementation of the Fisheries Conflict Database. Managed SQL database, conducted natural language processing, and conducted data analysis using Python.

Education

PhD University of Central Florida, Security Studies	2016 - 2020
MA University of New Orleans, Political Science	2014-2015
BA Auburn University, Political Science	2010 - 2014

Professional Skills

- Technical Skills: Python, R, SQL, MongoDB, ArcGIS, Stata, Git, Tableau, PowerBI, Java, Spark
- Theoretical Skills: Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Deep-Learning, Time Series, Econometric modeling, Web Development, Database Management, Spatial Analysis, Research Design, Survey and Experiment Design, Experienced oral and written communicator.
- Team and Leadership Skills: Multiple collaborative publications with interdisciplinary scientists.
 Managed teams of researchers, guided project design and implementation of data collection and analysis. Held several elected leadership positions including Student Government Vice President.

Publications

- 3 peer-reviewed | 1 book Chapter | 1 under review 2 policy reports | 4 popular articles | Google Scholar
 - 11. **Joshua E. Lambert**, Graham Epstein, Jennifer Joel, and Jacopo Baggio. "Introducing the Commons Synthesis Project: Topics and trends in the study of common-pool resource", *International Journal of the Commons*, **2021**.
 - Sarah M. Glaser, Colleen Devlin, Joshua E. Lambert, and Ciera Villegas, "The Causes and Consequences of Fisheries Conflict around the Horn of Africa", forthcoming - Journal of Peace Research, 2021.
 - 9. **Joshua E. Lambert**, Mark Schafer, Stephen Walker, and Collin Kazazis, "Presidential Personalities and Operational Codes: Learning Effects and Midterm Congressional Election Results", Book Chapter in *Operational Code Analysis and Foreign Policy Roles Crossing Simons Bridge*, **2021**.
 - 8. Mark Schafer and **Joshua E. Lambert**, "Psychological Characteristics of Leaders (PsyCL): Introducing a New Data Set", *Under Review*.
 - 7. **Joshua E. Lambert** and Anthony Licciardi, "What belief in extraterrestrial visitors to Earth reveals about trust in elections", *The Conversation*, **2021**.
 - Christopher M. Faulkner, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jonathan Powell, "Reassessing Private Military and Security Company(PMSC) 'Competition' in Civil War: Lessons from Sierra Leone" Small Wars and Insurgencies, 2019.
 - 5. Eric Keels, Jay Benson, John Filitz, and **Joshua E. Lambert**, "Reassessing Rebellion", *One Earth Future*, **2019**.
 - 4. Eric Keels and **Joshua E. Lambert**, "Why Sudan's deadly crackdown on protesters could escalate in coming weeks", *The Conversation*, **2019**.
 - 3. Christopher Faulkner, **Joshua E. Lambert**, and Jonathan Powell, "Peeling back the layers on the role of private security companies in Africa", *The Conversation*, **2019**.
 - 2. Sarah M. Glaser, Colleen Devlin, **Joshua E. Lambert**, Ciera Villegas, and Natasia Poinsatte, "Fish Wars: The Causes and Consequences of Fisheries Conflict in Tanzania", *One Earth Future*, **2019**.
 - 1. Clayton Besaw, **Joshua E. Lambert**, and Jean-Pierre Larroque, "Rulers, Elections, and Irregular Governance (REIGN) Showcase: Part I", *One Earth Future*, **2018**.

3 Working manuscripts

- 3. Güneş Murat Tezcür and **Joshua E. Lambert**, "Global Patterns in Religion and Large Scale Violence"
- 2. Christopher Faulkner and **Joshua E. Lambert**, "Coup-Proofing, Mutinies, and Private Military and Security Companies"
- 1. **Joshua E. Lambert**, "Them Belly Full but We Hungry: Food Insecurity as an Elite Motivator for Coups"

Teaching

Adjunct Lecturer/Instructor of Record (e.g., Jupyter notebook.)

University of Central Florida, Orlando | School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

GIS for Political Analysis

Fall 2019, Spring 2020

Graduate Teaching Assistant

University of Central Florida, Orlando | School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

Courses included: 2016- 2018

International Relations, Comparative Politics, Geography, Political Science, Public Policy

Presentations

14 invited conference presentations

- 2021 International Studies Association (Remote), American Political Science Association (Seattle, WA)
- o 2020 International Studies Association (Cancelled Honolulu, HI)
- o 2019 International Studies Association (Toronto, CAN)
- o 2018 Southern Political Science Association (New Orleans, LA)
- 2017 Florida Political Science Association (Orlando, FL); Southwestern Political Science
 Association (Austin, TX); International Society of Political Psychology Association (Edinburgh, SCT); International Studies Association South (Orlando, FL)
- 2014 Alabama Political Science Association (Montgomery, AL); Southern Political Science Association (New Orleans, LA)
- o 2013 Alabama Political Science Association (Tuscaloosa, AL)

Awards, Outreach and Service

ViEWS Conflict Forecasting Competition invited participant – Uppsala, SWE	2020
PRIO Conflict Trends Course participant – Oslo, NOR	2018
President, Political Science Graduate Student Association (UCF) SciPy conference workshop participant – Austin, TX	2018 - 2019 2018
GEOINT Symposium participant – Tampa Bay, FL	2018
DIA Summer Seminar participant – Washington D.C.	2017
UCF Political Science Colloquium presenter – Orlando, FL	2017
Florida Political Science Graduate Paper Winner – Orlando, FL	2017
ISPP Summer Methodology Academy participant – Edinburgh, SCT	2017
UNO Student Government Senator of the year – New Orleans, LA	2015
Vice President, Student Government Association (UNO)	2015
Member, Dean Search Committee (UNO)	2015
Senator, Student Government Association (UNO)	2014 - 2015

References

1. Jonathan Powell | Committee Chair

Associate Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Jonathan.Powell@ucf.edu | 407-823-2082

2. Konstantin Ash | Committee Co-Chair

Assistant Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Konstantin.Ash@ucf.edu | 407-823-2608

3. Peter Jacques | Committee Member

Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Peter.Jacques@ucf.edu | 407-823-6773

4. Güneş Murat Tezcür | Supervisor

Professor and Jalal Talabani Chair of Kurdish Political Studies

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Tezcur@ucf.edu | 407-823-2040